BENJAMIN MARCHANT

DATA SCIENTIST / STRUCTURAL ENGINEER

- bemarchant@proton.me
- linkedin.com/in/bemarchant
- github.com/bemarchant
- +569 45515501
- /portfolio/bemarchant

EDUCATION

ACADEMIC BACKGROUND

Bachelor of Structural Engineering Pontificia Universidad Católica de Chile. 2015 - 2018

Erasmus Exchange Uppsala University, Sweden. Aug. 2016 - Jan. 2017

Bachelor of Natural Sciences and **Mathematics**

Pontificia Universidad Católica de Chile. 2012 - 2015

Highschool

Colegio Concepción San Pedro, Chile. 2007 - 2011

SELF-LEARNING COURSES

- Applied Machine Learning in Python University Of Michigan May. 2023 4 wks
- Introduction to Data Science in Python University Of Michigan Apr. 2023 4 wks

Jumpstart the Raspberry Pi Pico Udemy Apr. 2022 4 hrs

Macro photography Biodiversidad Chile Apr. 2021 6 hrs

Bird photography

Indomito Apr. 2021 6 hrs

Mountaineering Club Andino Universitario Apr. 2018 - Oct. 2018 7 mos

English

Instituto Chileno Británico de Cultura 2005 - 2010 5 yrs

ADDITIONAL INFORMATION

SIDE PROJECTS

(click on the project for more info)

Tomorrow's Netflix stock price

• Invasive species in Antarctica

Model of living systems

Bird's calls memory game

SKILLS

Python

Github

★ Visual Studio Code

Inkscape

C#

SQLite

Microsoft Excel

LANGUAGES

Spanish Native

English Fluently

HOBBIES

Rock Climbing

Wildlife Photography

PROFESSIONAL PROFILE

Structural engineer with strong understanding in linear algebra, physics and passionate about programming.

Experienced in computational geometry, numerical methods and data management resulted from 2D/3D modelling. Complete understanding of math behind a structural software.

Passionate about team working, self-teaching. Rock climb instructor at mountaineering Club Andino Universitario.

WORK EXPERIENCE

WILDLIFE CONSULTANT

Sept. 2022 - Apr. 2023

Fundación Andescalada

Foundation that coordinates the sustainable development of climbing areas in Chile.

Collected data about flora, fauna and funga in Cajón del Maipo, El Manzano. By retrieving data from trail cameras, iNaturalist API and field work within a presence-absence methodology. Retrieved 524 observations (80% of the total data) from iNaturalist database in Python, managed it with Pandas and NumPy, and visualited on Matplotlib.

Spoke on wildlife talks for the community. Involved them into activelly participation by reporting species. The data collected contributes 56% of the total species reported. Adding 167 new species which 50% comes from community participation during the project.

COMPUTATIONAL GEOMETRY SOFTWARE ENGINEER

Oct. 2021 - Sep. 2022

Structure Stech

Develops plugins for construction industries with innovative solutions that enhance productivity and optimize processes.

Improved users experience by developing 2D/3D geometrical algorithms for the automatization of drawing routines in construction industry. Reduced time, effort and productivity for repetitive tasks of magnitude around months to few-clicks tasks done within days.

Collaborated on *Gravity*, a private **desktop application** for structural analysis and concrete design. Developed unique tools for structurals engineers.

Worked on a .NET Core framework. Visual Studio as the development environment, **C#** as the programming language, **git** and **github** for team collaboration.

SEISMIC CONSULTANT

Jul. 2019 - Aug. 2021 2 yrs 2 mos

₽ EQCO, Earthquake Engineering Consultants

Recently established as the organizational front end for providing Consulting Services in Earthquake Engineering.

Provided consulting service to different projects in the area of Earthquake Engineering. Worked on structures like: hydroelectric, electrical equipment, eolic parks and jetties.

Developed Python scripts for running models. Automatized processes of weeks duration into hours. Reduced time of non-linear wind turbines modelling around 80%.

Cleaned and **interpreted data** results from structurals 2D/3D model's results. Used of Python libraries: NumPy, Pandas and Matplotlib.

SUMMER JOB

Jan. 2019 1 mos

SIRVE S.A., Seismic Protection Technologies

Data collection of structures materials from buildings across the route of Santiago metro line 7.

Statistical analysis to prevent damage in cultural heritage structures to control vibration serviceability of residential buildings.

Reported results served for the design of a solution to reduce vibrations without reducing the speed operability.

INTERNSHIP

Dec. 2016 - Jan. 2017 2 mos

Bechtel Chile Ltda.

Supported in Quebrada Blanca Phase 2, a mining project.

Organizing data of the project's quantity take-off, search for missing data and text inconsistencies.

Filled QB2's project quantities on Bechtel's database by writing Excel macro scripts. Reduced time for the task from a week to one day, allowed me to focus only on errors and inconsistencies.